[Music]
in 2019 dr david katz and colleagues
including one of my favorite researchers
david jenkins published a public health
case for modernizing the definition of
protein quality the prevailing
definition seems to have more to do with
biochemistry than the net effects on
human health the popular concept that
protein is good and the more the better
coupled with a protein quality
definition that favors animal protein
fosters the impression that eating more
meat eggs and dairy is desirable
preferable but this is directly opposed
to nutrition guidelines that are instead
trying to push more plants although
protein malnutrition is still prevalent
in many areas of the world it is
exceedingly rare in the industrialized
world where the most formidable public
health threat is not something like
kwashiorkor protein calorie malnutrition
but from chronic diseases
in 2016 a landmark study was published
out of harvard involving more than a
hundred thousand people that found that
replacing animal protein with plant
protein was associated with lower risk
of dying prematurely the worst seemed to
be processed meat like bacon as well as
egg protein the egg whites but swapping
in even just three percent plant protein
for any of the animal proteins processed
meat unprocessed meat chicken fish eggs
or dairy was associated with a
significantly lower risk of arguably the
most important endpoint of all
death
yeah but how do we know it's the protein
the researchers adjusted for factors
such as saturated fat intake which
suggested it wasn't just the animal fat
okay but how does your body even know
the difference between protein from a
plant and protein from an animal isn't
protein protein no
unlike animal protein plant proteins
generally low in branched chain amino
acids for example and decreased
consumption of branched chain amino
acids improves metabolic health
it could be the igf-1 a cancer-promoted
growth hormone that is boosted by
so-called high-quality animal protein
intake though we suspect the igf-1
connection is cause and effect since
people who are born to have higher igf-1
levels regardless of what they do appear
to suffer higher rates of killers like
type 2 diabetes and heart disease
or it could be something that harvard
researchers didn't control for such as
toxic pollutants like dioxins and pcbs
since they tend to accumulate up the
food chain and cattle pigs chickens and
fish and therefore end up on our plates
so plant-based protein also stands as an
important step to lower the body burden
of harmful pollutants
if you don't think a hundred thousand
people are enough how about four hundred
thousand people the nih aarp study is
the largest diet cohort study in history
and again simply swapping three percent
of calories from various animal protein
sources with plant protein was
associated with 10 percent decreased
overall mortality and you get even twice
that benefit if you get rid of eggs too
that's not a surprise since egg
consumption is associated with a higher
risk of developing cardiovascular
disease
put all the studies together on dietary
protein intake and mortality and people
who eat more protein tend to live
shorter lives but this is mainly driven
by the harmful association of animal
protein plant protein intake is
inversely associated with mortality
meaning those who eat more plant protein
tend to live longer lives
more animal protein may mean more
mortality whereas more plant proteins
correlated with less mortality so the
best of both worlds would be to increase
the intake of plant protein in place of
animal protein in other words as another
2020 meta-analysis concluded
persons should be encouraged to increase
their plant protein intake to
potentially decrease their risk of death
[Music]
so
you